A Guide to the Lemuel C. Sheperd Papers, 1913-1970
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
Lemuel C. Shepherd Papers, 1913-1970
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
mss 00006
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were donated by Lemuel C. Shepherd.
Biographical/Historical Information
Lemuel C. Shepherd
Significant Events
1896 February 10 Born in Norfolk, Virginia.
1917 June Graduated from the Virginia Military Institute.
1917-1919 Served with the 5th Marines, 2nd Division, American Expeditionary Forces, France.
1920-1922 Aide to the Commandant of the Marines Corps; junior White House aide.
1922 Married Virginia Tunstall Driver. They had four children.
1922-1925 Served on U. S. Ships, Idaho and Nevada.
1927-1929 Served with the 4th Marines in China.
1937-1939 Commander, 2nd Battalion, 5th Marines, 1st Marine Brigade, Fleet Marine Force.
1939-1942 Staff member, Marine Corps School.
1942-1943 Regimental Commander, 9th Marines, 3rd Marine Division.
1943-1944 Assistant Division Commander, 1st Marine Division.
1944-1945 Commanding General, 6th Marine Division.
1946-1948 Assistant Commandant and Chief of Staff, Marine Corps.
1948-1950 Commandant, U. S. Marine Corps Schools.
1950-1951 Commanding General, Fleet Marine Force, Pacific.
1952-1956 Commandant, Marine Corps.
1956 Retired from Marine Corps. Served as Chairman, Inter-American Defense Board.
1990 August 6 Died at his home in La Jolla, California. Buried Arlington National Cemetery.
Scope and Content Information
The Lemuel C. Shepherd Papers consist primarily of photograph albums and scrapbooks dating from Shepherd's years as a VMI cadet, as Commandant of the Marine Corps, and from his service as President of the Inter-American Defense Board. Topics included in this pictorial record are inspection trips to Japan, Korea, Okinawa and stateside bases, as well as visits to several Latin American Countries. Also included are photographs from the surrender ceremony at Tsingao, China, October 25, 1945.
The collection also contains limited correspondence and military orders from the World War I and II eras; an interview with General Shepherd conducted by the archivist of the MacArthur Library; clippings; and printed material.
Contents List
- Correspondence (Miscellaneous), 1944-1946 (Box-folder 1:1-9)
  This correspondence is miscellaneous in nature and consists of fewer than 20 items. Correspondents and topics include: Mobert Bonhomme; Nagano Eiji (Japanese General); Chaplain W. F. McClain; Mrs. Lemuel C. Shepherd; Guam Liberation Day; a form letter for the sympathy message sent to parents of soldiers killed in action.
- Interview with General L. C. Shepherd, 1966 August 24 (Box-folder 1:10)
  Transcript of an oral history interview conducted by the archivist at the MacArthur Library.
- Addresses by General Shepherd, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 1:11)
  Talks given to troops and officers.
- Military Orders, 1918-1919; 1945 (Box-folder 1:12-13)
  Includes both printed and typescript/signed documents.
- Scrapbooks, 1913-1955 (Box 2 and 3)
  - VMI Cadet Scrapbook 1913-1917
  - Pre-World War II career. 1920's-1930's
    Primarily clippings; also some memorabilia, including invitations from Mrs. Roosevelt and a thank you note signed by President Franklin D. Roosevelt.
  - Marines in World War II- General.
    Primarily newspaper clippings concerning Guam and New Britain.
  - Marines in World War II--6th Marine Division
    Primarily clippings concerning Okinawa; limited memorabilia.
  - Inspection Trip, Japan. 1955 April
    Includes clippings, postcards, photographs, printed materials.
  - Military Insignia of French Colonial Troops. 1955 April
    A collection of approximately 35 metal insignias.
- Photographs and Photo Albums, 1945-1959 (Box 4 - 6)
  - Surrender Ceremony, Tsingtao, China. 1945 October 25
  - Douglas MacArthur at Pearl Harbor. 1951 April 16-17
  - Trips-Marine Corps-Inspection of U. S. Forces 1953-1955
    Includes visits to Korea, Yokosura Marine Barracks, Camp Pendleton, 3rd Marine Aircraft Wing (Miami).
  - Trips-Marines Corps-other 1955 March
    Argentina, Brazil
  - Trips, Inter-American Defense Board 1956-1959
    Argentina, Bolivia, Cuba, Haiti, Paraguay, Peru.
- Report. My Visit to Japan, 1945 September. (Box-folder 1:14)
- WWII-miscellaneous. (Box-folder 1:15-17)
  Notes concerning origin of Japanese sword of surrender; circular, Japanese propaganda; citation for distinguished service medal.
- Printed Materials. (Box 1)
  Includes various pamphlets, magazines and yearbooks, most relating to Marine Corps during World War II.